CHANGING LIVES
Emanuel! God is with us! Viewers around the world, welcome to today's episode of changing lives.
My name is Chris.
My name is Olamide.
This is the programme where we personally encounter those who have personally encountered
Jesus Christ in a special way through the ministry that God has given to Prophet T.B. Joshua
Yes, Chris. Today, we live in a world where many view life as fun and games.
They pursue pleasure at the price of peace
but always end up being left with a sense of dissatisfaction in life.
That's very true, Olamide.
By the grace of God, the life experience of the couple that we have with us here today
on changing lives is a very poignant reminder that life is indeed not fun and games.
In fact, viewers, it is a warfare where only the serious-minded are victorious.
Yes, indeed. Little did our guests know that life did not just happen to him.
It's all about choices and how he responded to every situation.
Before his success came, he made many wrong choices in the past that almost crippled his marriage,
his professional life but when he connected to the anointing that breaks the yoke
here at The SCOAN, that was when he rediscovered his roots
and began to walk into his divine destiny - both personally and professionally.
Today we have the pleasure of speaking with one of Nigeria's most celebrated film critic and scholar.
He is a publisher, an author and also a PhD holder from the University of Warwick in the United Kingdom.
He is also the sitting dean of the Faculty of Humanities at the University of Port Harcourt, River State, Nigeria.
He is also a member of the university's governing council.
You're welcome to this programme, Prof. Femi Shaka and his wife.
Thank you for joining us on this programme.
- It's been a pleasure.
- You're welcome.
Tell us more about yourself and tell us the reason why you're here on the programme today.
I am Professor Femi Okiremuete Shaka.
I studied at the universities of Benin, Ibadan in Nigeria, and then proceeded to the United Kingdom
on commonwealth scholarship to take a PhD in film studies at the University of Warwick, Coventry.
Thereafter, I returned to Nigeria in 1995 to take up an appointment at the University of Port Harcourt.
But the story is a little bit full of disappointment, near success situations and so on and so forth.
Returning from the UK with a PhD in film studies, which was very rare at the time I got it,
I expected that the university would grab me and be very happy to have somebody
in a new discipline in the country.
But my employment was delayed for one full year, and I couldn't understand it.
It was as if all the expectations I had in coming back...
I had the opportunity of going to Canada, Australia or the US
but I decided to come home to pass on the knowledge.
So you can imagine the feeling of disappointment I had when my employment was delayed.
Since then, I've been having a lot of delays in life expectations.
About 1995 or thereabout, I met my wife.
She was doing a programme then at the university.
I had just returned. We met, dated for a couple of years and then got married.
In 2001, the year of 9/11, I got a Fulbright scholarship to go back to the US.
I taught and carried out research at the New York University -
African and African-American studies programme.
I was there for one year, and it was during that tenure there that I wrote my book on African cinema.
When I returned, I got really distracted.
First I got elected into the senior staff club of the university.
University in Nigeria are almost a small community of their own.
Most of them have staff quarters, health centres, primary school for the children of staff,
nursery and high school.
The high school is like a teaching laboratory for students specialising in education.
So I got elected into the staff club and that is where my life started going down the drain
because I then started indulging and drinking.
Most of the time I used to boast to my friends that my movement was triangular.
If you didn't find me in the house, I had gone for lectures.
Then there were two places you could get me - if I was not in the lecture room,
I would be in the staff club, and if I was not in the staff club, I would be in the house.
I spent most of the time in the staff club drinking with my friends,
arguing over nothing.
And you can imagine that when you've taken a long drink and you're high,
when you see all your friends phoning their girlfriends, telling them to come over
to join them at the staff club, you are tempted to join them and I did join them.
Very soon, I became an expert.
Whenever you are traveling for external examination, you would talk about, "Oh boy. Are you carrying a handbag?"
I mean, such kind of misogynistic expressions.
The grace of God was upon my work because I noticed that each time I went out on these exploits,
she would usually catch me.
When you say that you were carrying a handbag, you need to explain it a bit.
It is a girlfirend.
It refers to a girlfriend - handbag.
When you are travelling, you are supposed to carry a handbag.
Men don't carry handbags which tells you the derogatory language we used for our women.
From my own personal experience, it was something that was destroying me and my career.
Rather than really publishing and getting celebrated, I was going down
because I was spending more time in the staff club than at my desk as a researcher,.
I should have been spending more time burning the midnight oil and reading and publishing papers.
That was when my promotion got delayed again for about eight years, even though I was well published.
I'm sorry to cut in - could you just tell us of the scale and scope of the kind of alcohol you were taking,
as a result of this lifestyle.
It was much.
We used to boast.
I would say, "Get me an electric pole". An electric pole is like a big bottle of stout, and then you mix it with coke.
You can take about four of that.
You would have just finished from the lecture hall and come to the club. You had not eaten.
So most of the time, you were high and lost track of things.
You would not be thinking straight as you should as a scholar,
and you weren't really paying more attention to your studies and teaching.
Your teaching is based on the experiences you have picked up.
You are supposed to do a lot of research before you go to the classroom to teach.
I was a stickler for time and everything but even at my own level of education
I could feel that I wasn't doing what I ought to do.
I mean, by the kind of instruction I was put through in the UK, I knew I wasn't giving my best,
even though among my colleagues, I was celebrated as one of the best lecturers in my department.
I even won some awards - three or four years as the best teacher in the department.
But I knew within me that I could do better than what I was doing.
So my kids were not really seeing me. I was an absentee father.
Whenever they called me and said, "Daddy, there's homework",
I would say, "Please give it to your mom or to the lesson teacher!"
I would just storm out and the house was very hot for me.
I just couldn't understand why I couldn't feel comfortable in my house - the house was just hot.
I just had to get out. When I was driving to the staff club, that is when I would feel free, happy and relaxed.
But it wasn't the best of life.
My promotion, like I said, was delayed by eight years.
It gave me some time to think over my life,
"What is happening to me? Where am I? I mean, I have a Christian upbringing.
So what is happening to me?"
Sorry to cut you short.
During this time were your students and fellow lecturers aware of your activities outside the university?
No way! They weren't aware.
I was living a secret life - a very secret life.
Most of the time I thought I was deceiving my wife but the grace of God was upon her.
Like I said, she would always catch me in the act.
One time I asked her, "Is anybody telling you what I'm doing
or how come you are always catching me when I go out?"
She would say, "Look. Unless you come out of your escapades, sinful life -
the Lord will clean you up first before you will start to see your life, visions
the way they are supposed to come".
I would laugh over it.
My sister-in-law came to the house.
I was always very moody because my promotion had been delayed.
Many people whom I felt were not well published as I was were getting promoted.
I was complaining and she asked whether we had heard about Emmanuel TV.
Sorry to cut you again, sir. Before you talk about discovering Emmanuel TV,
we still want our viewers to really learn from what you're talking about - your experience with this lifestyle.
Did you at any time consider the risks or the repercussions of such a lifestyle?
Of course no!
Anybody who is into smoking or is into a particular lifestyle
does not really see that there are repercussions.
I mean I could have contracted a disease and passed it on to my wife.
Both of us could have died. What about the kids that we brought into the world?
I didn't really give any thought to that.
As far as I was concerned, I was seeking pleasure and I was getting plenty of it.
A university like ours - because I was also dedicated to my duty in a way, compared to other lecturers.
Girls were around; they were always coming around.
There was a lot of temptation in getting really sunk into that kind of whirlpool of sinfulness
Something that I can say - only the good Lord pulled me out of it
because I mean, how do you live a life where you are a stranger before your kids?
Each time you come, it is as if everybody starts hiding
and talks like, "Daddy has come back!" They would start shouting that.
I would start shouting, asking for my food.
If my food did not come quickl, I would go up straight to my bed.
I knew I was hurting my wife but I was helpless
because there was a spirit driving me that I couldn't control and contain.
So maybe we can see you actually in a world of your own.
Yes, and many of my colleagues are living the same kind of life.
Many of them are still into it, even as I'm speaking now.
Many of them are in the club drinking, shouting and arguing over nonsense.
Their families are lonely.
Their wife and children really deserve to have their father in the home.
I was absent.
Thank You, Father.
So then what you thought you were doing to create pleasure for yourself,
can we say that it actually satisfied you or you felt fulfilled during that time?
No, I was empty and looking for more of it!
There was a time before I travelled to the US, we would boast,
"Oh boy, which one?" - "Number two has gone!"
Only for God's sake.
God loved me. If not, by now I'm sure I would have been dead.
For the abuse I gave to myself.
Thinking back now, I was really self-centred.
I never really gave a thought to my wife about what I was doing.
It was really a very bad life.
I'd like to ask your wife a question at this point.
Your husband said you caught him many times, even red-handed.
In fact, almost all the time.
Did you ever consider leaving him when you caught him in such a scenario?
No.
Why? What strengthened you?
My own brain game because I attended a seminary school,
and it really helped me knowing the Lord.
And I knew when we came together, I had to pray because of the challenges in the marriage.
He is from Orugu, I'm from Igbo.
You hardly see a Yoruba man, being the first son, marrying outside.
So there were a lot of challenges before we came together.
Sometimes my friends would say, "Won't you leave him? Orugu people will kill you!"
Yes.
Then I started putting it into prayer.
And I then noticed...
Even during that period, in year 1, I had it very hot with the family.
It wasn't an easy journey.
At the time, instead of going for my lectures, we were together, we were like friends.
Like he rightly said, we courted for some time.
So I started going to church, trying to seek the face of the Lord.
In fact, instead of going to lectures, when there were challenges, I would go to church.
Sometimes this apostolic - you would follow the congregation and then a message would come,
"You're crying, what did you do?
God said you didn't do anything. He will fight the battle".
In fact, all these messages that were coming made me to stay put.
So all the challenges - it wasn't an easy journey.
If you don't know the Lord, you will collapse. Yes.
So when we started, he was really a nice person - at that early time.
When I just came back from the UK.
Very nice.
So at the time, when we got married, the house was very hot.
I said, "What is going on?"
Each time he went clubbing; when he came back to the house, it was just to have his bath and then off again.
He changed and then off again.
I asked, "Won't you eat?" He said, "No, no!"
By the time he came back, maybe around nine or ten, he would say, "Where is my food?"
Or sometimes there would be food on the dining table, he would say, "No, no!"
I would say, "You see what you are doing to yourself", and he would go upstairs.
Even in the marriage, I lost two kids.
I lost the first one, the second one was dead, and I lost the third one.
When I was pregnant for the fourth one, I remember one experience - a very sad experience.
He was going out in the morning. He came because I saw him with a lady.
In the morning I said, "Who was that person?"
He said, "Must I know everybody?"
I said, "You are not going anywhere".
So when I said you're not going anywhere, he pushed me with the pregnancy.
I fell.
So when I fell, I stood up.
He said, "I will go and report you to your parents, if you want somebody that will kill you".
I'm sure you are feeling bad.
He said, "If you want somebody that will kill his mommy, go to your parents and die there".
I left him.
So when I left him, my spirit said - because before then, each time I complained to his mother,
since they didn't like me then - that was then -
so each time I complained, they would say, "Ehe".
His mum told me one day, "My husband married three - from polygamous home. I didn't kill him.
So you will not kill my son because of women. If you don't want to stay, go!"
So because of that, I now stopped complaining.
So when he did that to me, when he pushed me, I told myself...
All these things that had been happening, I refused to tell my own people
because I knew they loved him. I didn't want them to hate him -
for them to feel that he was treating me badly.
I was keeping it all to myself, praying.
So when he pushed me, one spirit said, "Don't push him, leave him!
Just focus on God. God will change him
If you continue like this, you will get yourself hurt. You'll be hurting yourself.
Leave him. The battle is not yours; it is the Lord's".
The Spirit of God kept talking inside of me.
Each time the Spirit of God talked to me, I would relax.
So that day when he came back, I was lying down on the floor in the sitting room.
He left that morning and came back around 6:00.
I was expecting him to say like, "Are you okay?" He didn't talk to me. He just walked on.
Each time I would be the one to meet him to say, "It's okay"
because I knew he was ever ready to dump me to move ahead with his life.
So it would be me to break the silence.
And you cannot continue this way because anything that will bring enmity will go to God.
God will not hear you.
Each time I would still be the one going to him, saying, "Okay. That one has past. It is okay".
I would waive it.
So we continued like that.
There were instances - they were too many.
There was one time, during one of the periods that I lost a baby, pregnancy was not coming.
I stayed up to five years (without getting pregnant).
Pregnancy was not coming.
I had just lost that baby like a month.
I went to my doctor at Aba - from Port Harcourt to Aba.
That morning he dressed up. He was going to the presidential palace to give a talk.
I said, "You are looking good". He said, "Thank you".
When I left, he gave me money to go and see my doctor.
I came back in the evening around 4:00.
From the taxi I was in, I saw him.
They drove past.
The girl was sitting this way, facing him.
In my mind I said, "What is this.
Look at you now. You've come to look at him enjoying himself. It is well".
So I went home.
As I was there, one of my friends came that her husband was doing the same thing.
She just came to me and said, "Mrs Shaka, when my husband comes, today A.
In fact, today, we will fight".
I said, "Fight? Why?"
She said, "This man - carrying women!"
I said, "Hmm".
So we were discussing and I was counselling her, "Leave it! Pray for him!"
As we were talking, I told her about the one I had seen that very day.
"I went to Aba for treatment. I saw him coming.
He went to the presidential palace, and I saw him when he was coming back".
She said, "What is with all these men?" We laughed.
We were discussing when my husband came.
He parked his car in the garage and then entered.
I said, "Honey, welcome".
He said, "Thank you".
I said, "You stayed long. Is it that since this morning, you just finished?"
He said, "Yes". That was around 7:00.
He said, "Yes, we just closed now".
So the lady looked at my face. I looked at her as soon as he went upstairs.
She said, "Wow. You are doing well. You mean since 4 o'clock that you saw him?"
I said, "Yes. Now he will go and arrange himself".
She said, "If it were me, as he entered, I would grab him".
I said, "No, you don't need to do that".
So it was that very night that I caught him again.
I said, "This thing you are doing, is it good?
This morning, you gave me money to go and see my doctor.
As I was coming back - look at me going - we have only one son.
Look at me going, pursuing the fruit of the womb.
Look at you. Look at what you are doing with women. Is it good?
If it is good before God, it is good before me.
But if it is not good before God, okay, let Him fight the battle.
Stop doing this thing".
Wow. We really salute your patience. We really do.
Indeed, you felt relaxed. It is all to the glory of God.
Whenever I talked to him that way - you wouldn't see me shouting.
The Spirit of God said, "Don't shout. It is not your battle.
Continue talking to him. I will fight it for you".
Each time I would talk to him gently, nicely.
I would say, "It is not good".
He would be sober.
He would say, "I'm sorry".
I would say, "It's okay. Bring your hand".
I would hold his hand and pray for him.
I would say, "Stop doing these things. Let us see where God will take us".
He would say, "Okay".
After that "okay", he would leave that particular one.
Anyone I discovered, he would leave that one.
And go to another one.
I realised that when I got that one, he would leave that one.
I would tell him, "You drive this one away and then jump here to this one".
I would be teasing him with it.
Sometimes too, instead of quarrelling when he got home...
Sometimes, when he saw that I had caught him, I would call him and say, "Where are you?"
He would say, "I'm going to the club." Then I would say, "I'm coming to the club too to drink".
He would then say, "No, no. I'm not in the club. My car got spoiled".
I would say, "You see your life! You cannot hide it from God!"
I would sing that song.
When he came back, I would say, "You see yourself? All these girls!
The day I will catch them, I will squeeze their heads".
He would say, "Don't mind them - all these stupid girls!
So I now turned it to a game so that I would not hurt myself.
He would say, "Mummy, don't worry - all these girls".
It is exactly what your husband was saying earlier.
It was a spirit behind it.
I knew that it was a spirit.
That was why I noticed that my rate of progress was going down.
I was not living up to expectations.
I was supposed to be a high flyer but I was not making progress.
My sister-in-law noticed it also because she came to the house.
Most of the time, they loved me - my in-laws.
Instead of calling me by name, they were calling me "Unlce Femi". They were very fond of me.
She was asking me, "What is wrong? Why is your promotion so delayed?"
I said, "I don't know.
She then asked, "Are you aware of Emmanuel TV?"
I said, "No".
She then said, "You need to install it in the house and be watching it".
That is one of the things that I most credit my wife with: She is very determined.
Shortly after that, she installed Emmanuel TV.
We started watching it, keenly.
We saw the wonderful things that God was using His servant, Prophet T.B. Joshua,
to achieve amongst His people.
Like I have said, because I come from a Christian family background,
I saw immediately that I needed to seek spiritual direction.
I knew that there was something pushing me.
It was like someone smoking - the more the person promises he is going to stop smoking,
the more the spirit of smoking would take hold of the person.
This was the kind of thing I was going through.
We watched Emmanuel TV in our house for nearly one year
before I ventured to travel to The SCOAN.
When I came, I had the opportunity of getting the Morning Water.
I went back home with it.
We would say a prayer,
and at the end of the prayer, I would administer the Morning Water on each member of the family.
When it reached my turn, I would confess all my sins - before my family, my mother-in-law.
That I was a fornicator, drunkard, that I was not doing my family duties,
that I wasn't a good father to my children. I had to confess all my sins.
My mother-in-law was laughing at me, "You are funny!"
I said, "I'm not funny because I must put this devil to shame!"
So to discrace this spirit?
Yes!
Each night he would pray, "God of T.B. Joshua, help me!
Every spirit of fornication and adultery, not being faithful to my dear wife, every spirit - out!"
All these things you were hiding came out.
The way he shouted, all of us would say, "That spirit - out, in the name of Jesus!"
You were doing mass prayer in your house!
Very shortly after that, after about two months - I kept on praying
but I did not notice that I had not been going to the club.
Just like that.
It kept on going like this for three months. Then people started calling me, "What is happening?
We don't see you at the club nowadays!"
I said, "It is because of work!"
This went on for six months.
Then it became clear that something was really happening.
Then I started not to feel the urge for going to the club, taking alcohol.
It just stopped.
The urge just left.
My former girlfriends lined up - they would call and call.
I'm sure they are watching now. You see? I'm born-again!
I'm delivered.
They kept calling and calling.
I sent most of them text messages, "Please, I'm born-again!"
Most of them didn't believe it because I was really bad.
I was living a bad life.
It went on like that.
They noticed that when the second examiner came,
I would take the person down to the club to buy them a drink - we would take maltina.
That was still initially. After that, I never went again to the club, at all.
It was February last year that I celebrated my wife.
I said, "Do you know that this is the first time since I married you that I can really say
that I'm celebrating Valentine's day without having seen another woman for one year".
And I said, "Wow, God is great!"
Since then, I have been having a peaceful home - a settled home.
I'm at peace with myself and I keep asking myself, "What the hell was I doing in the club?"
About January - Febuary last year, a group of young men in the faculty came to me and said,
"Prof, you have to be our next dean".
I said, "Me?"
So they laughed.
Before I knew it, they went and picked forms, filled forms, printed posters.
This happened on my behalf.
I couldn't help but joining them.
He didn't pay a dime.
They paid the money. They said, "You must be our next dean!"
In fairness, they knew that I was always very fair and firm on any issue.
I never really liked people that suppressed younger colleagues for no reason.
So they were determined that I should be the next dean.
But I knew that I was also a minority.
To tell you that God of T.B. Joshua was really involved in my affairs, has taken hold of my affairs,
after separating me from the club, drunkenness, womanising and everything,
I was now ready to go.
We went into the election.
On the very day of the election, the godfather - the one they referred to as godfather -
he called the two River State indigenous candidates who were contesting against me.
He said, "One of them should step down".
Of course they refused, which meant that their vote was split.
And that gave me the honour, by the grace of God of T.B. Joshua, to win the election by just one vote.
Just one vote.
I think I got about 156, and the second person 155.
It wasn't the senate one.
Ok.
The first person got 46; the second person 59.
And you got 60.
Wow.
So that's it.
That's how I won that election, and I knew that the hand of God was upon my life.
That same year, we had...
Before that - during the campaigning for that election, he didn't go to the club.
It was a year after the transformation.
When they came, the people campaigning for them would ask them in the club,
"The person you are campaigning for is not coming? You are the one doing it".
Each time they came to the house, I would tell the campaign manager -
he would call me, "Are you praying?" and I would say, "Yes.
But there is one thing I want to tell you: A builder builds in vain without God,
A watchman watches in vain without God.
So you campaign in vain without God.
So as you are campaigning, make sure you involve God".
Wow. And truly God was involved!
So the breakthrough you were looking for, for many years, was coming!
And after I won that election, I received NUC accreditation.
The Nigerian University Commission is the federal government agency
that is in charge of regulating programmes in Nigerian universities.
If your programme is not approved, accredited, you cannot teach that course.
So I had eight departments that were undergoing NUC accreditation.
My faculty is made up of nine departments.
One was already accredited. So I had eight departments (undergoing accreditation).
We were living in a rickety facult building.
We had a new, uncompleted faculty building that was in the bush.
When I told them that I was going to move into that faculty building,
those guys laughed and said, "How can you say that we should move into this forest?
That is not possible!"
I went to meet the Vice Chancellor.
Luckily, he saw my vision and said, "The money we were going to give to you, we will split it in two.
We will give half to the contractor to complete the building, and you can move into it.
That was exactly what happened.
Even when he won that election - each time we prayed with the Morning Water -
because he went in with two points that he would move them to the faculty building
and he would give them full accreditation.
Other people campaigned with calumny. I told him, "Don't campaign against anybody.
Just tell them what you want to do for them".
I was telling the campaign manager, "Just tell them what you want to do for them.
Don't campaign against anybody".
When he then won, the next thing for God to do was to complete these other things.
So we would change our prayer points. Each time, we kept on changing them.
I would tell him, "This is the prayer point".
Because befor the elction, each time he was praying, I would say, "No, this one!
This is a selfish prayer. Say, God, let them know that you can.
Who told you you are the only qualified person! You will change it!"
When we started praying, "God of T.B. Joshua, let Your favour and mercy speak for us.
But above all, let Your will be done!"
So when he won that election, we then had to change the prayer point -
about the building, establishing those things.
We then said, "God, establish your finger. Tell them that You are the one that made him dean with one vote".
We then started praying for the faculty building.
I was doing my prayers at midnight - every Friday I do prayers at midnight.
Yes, twelve to three.
During that midnight prayer, she heard a voice saying, "Embargo".
During the midnight prayer, I heard, "Embargo".
I rushed up and woke him up. I said, "There is an embargo in that". We started praying.
"There is an embargo - a spiritual embargo - so that you will not be able to move there."
So we now took the Morning Water.
And administered it.
I said, "We will fast today - no food this Saturday".
All of us declared a fast.
"After the fasting, we will use the Morning Water, and then you take me to that building.
Let me see that building." A massive building inside the bush.
We finished with the Morning Water and climbed up.
I said, "You are the dean. Make a declaration.
The Bible says, Decree a thing and it shall come to pass.
So degree! Take!" I gave him the Morning Water.
We started administering it and then left.
After praying over the embargo, I was called by the Vice Chancellor.
Money was released to the contractor.
Some time this year, around February-March, the Vice Chancellor called most of his friends.
We gathered at his place.
We were drinking and relaxing. He then said, "There are council elections upcoming".
He wanted a quiet administration - an administration that is progress-driven,
with a focus on academic growth of the university.
He wanted people who could really join him in the vision he was trying to pursue for the university.
He was encouraging us that we should not sit on the fence.
That most of us should run for membership of the governing council.
So he started mentioning names. He mentioned three names.
And one of the persons he mentioned said, "Shaka".
And he said, "Yes, and Shaka".
I said to myself, "Wow, look at me!" I just came because I was invited.
I had thought it was just a meeting of friends.
Now, I had gotten nominated as a member of the governing council.
I went into that election and of course, I won again.
This time I knew that the hand of God was upon my life.
So what an incredible transformation!
It is a spiritual, physical, marital transformation!
We just give all the glory to God.
I think, sir, that you are in the position to give advice to our viewers all over the world,
watching you right now. What would you tell them, based on your life experiences?
What I would advise them is: Any person living a wayward life,
there is no way you can use will power to change your life.
You have to submit your life totally to God.
As evangelists at The SCOAN often say, "Go to any living church" - fine!
But I want to say that when you have tried all the living churches and they have failed you,
please come to Lagos - come down here and seek the face of God.
This is where I got my liberation, and this is where I will recommend.
If you are living a wayward life, staying more at clubs, drinking from one club to another,
womanising and you can't help yourself, please seek the face of God.
Thank you very much.
Madam, what is your best advice you would also give to a spouse
whose partner is having a destructive addiction?
Ok. My advice is: They should depend on God.
They cannot do it on their own. They can't change them.
We cannot change them.
I was unable to change my husband but I depended on God,
knowing full well that He is the author and finisher of our faith.
And again He says, "I am the God of all flesh. Is there anything too difficult for me to do?"
Absolutely nothing!
I would also advise spouses that they should always forgive their spouse.
They should forgive. They should not hold anything against them
because it is just like you are holding somebody or yourself.
If you hold somebody like this, you too are not free - you are holding yourself.
Release them with forgiveness so that you too will be free.
Madam, you can obviously confirm the changes in your husband's life
since his deliverance and freedom.
Yes, a lot of changes.
Not going to the club.
Now, from the office you can boastfully say that at 4 or 5pm, daddy is at home.
And when he comes back to the house, he doesn't go anywhere.
Except maybe we are going for fellowship or any other outing that is not clubbing or woman-matter.
A lot of changes. In fact, God is faithful.
He is indeed faithful.
And the best thing that can happen to a family is when both of the couple are in the Lord,
when you are working together.
Not this one doing his own, this other person doing her own.
When the two minds are together, you will see that you will get there.
Amen.
Sometimes I would tell him, "You see, daddy, that God is faithful.
See the way the Lord is beautifying us. You see it because you are no longer doing those acts.
And each time I kept telling you that God will separate impurities before He will take you".
She was fond of telling me that.
Look at it! He has really separated impurities!
To God be the glory! And what about the relationship with the children?
The relationship - you see the children being very playful.
In fact, they are now even closer to him than to myself.
When he is back from work, you will see the childrein coming, "Daddy, I love you".
"Daddy, welcome."
You will see the closeness - they are closer to him than to myself now.
To Him be the glory!
That is why we are here - changing lives! The evidence of Christ Jesus is indeed lives changed.
Actually, a lot of viewers around the world watched your testimony
and were really touched with what the Lord has done for you.
So we have a couple of questions, just to round up the programme.
I have a question for Professor Femi here.
This is from a viewer in Zambia.
Alinvia in Zambia asks, "What is your message to the academicians
whose scientific frame of mind has often led them to doubt the reality of God's power?"
So there is an academic world like you find yourself in. What would be your message to them?
Well, I was very touched a couple of days ago when one of the evangelists came to preach to us.
That the chemical components that make up the human flesh have been scientifically proven.
That we are made up of sand. That is where we come from.
Science cannot solve the mysteries of this world.
I mean, I recollect that when I was in New York and went to the planetarium,
where you undertake a tour of the planets.
And I asked myself, "So if the scientists can imagine all these stars in our galaxy alone,
that you can't count, what makes you think that you can solve the riddle of God's creation?"
So science cannot answer all our questions.
We need to get back to God - the origin of our being and creation.
It does not mean that you will not ask scientific questions
but you must have God at the background and basis of your enquiry.
If not, you will get involved in things that will make you to doubt the existence of God
and that will be on the part of perdition.
Thank you very much for that.
Thank you very much.
We also have another question from our viewers.
It is actually a funny question.
It goes to you, madam.
It is from Betty. She says she is from Colorado in the United States.
She asks, "What stopped you from rebelling when you saw lipstick marks on your husband?"
Funny, indeed.
Because I knew he wasn't the one doing it.
I knew it was the spirit being.
I could not fight him but the spirit being.
Since I knew I could not fight the spirit being - it is God who can fight the spirit being -
so I moved it through that way in prayer.
Amen.
Wow, thank you. That is exactly what Prophet T.B. Joshua says,
"That if we fail to realise that there are powers that cause people to be bowed down in bondage,
we will continue to fight the wrong battle.
- It is the wrong battle.
- It is happening in many many homes today.
Fighting, quarrelling will bring tension in the house so there is no need.
Exactly. Wow. We really salute your faith, madam.
We thank God that today, testimony has resulted.
In fact, what changed him is because of me.
I have always called her the pastor of the family.
Because God really wanted to restore my peace.
So that was why He changed him.
Amen.
And you have actually made the right choice.
Because like the Bible says, The greatest decision you can make in life is to put your trust in God.
And that is what you have actually done. And He has actually seen you through everything.
That is one of my prayer points.
I pray it every day: Let nothing shake my confidence in Him!
Amen. Thank you so much, Professor Femi and Madam.
Thank you so much for joining us in 'Changing Lives'.
We believe that your experience has really blessed our viewers, and we thank you so much once again.
And also the best is yet to come in the family!
Better is not good enough, the best is yet to come!
CHANGING LIVES
In the course of this programme, we believe you have discovered the reality
that until you experience God, there will be dissatisfaction in your life.
No matter your status or stature in this world.
Indeed, viewers. You realised that education is good and wonderful but education is not success.
It is just to help us to get success when we carry God along.
And as Prophet T.B. Joshua says, "If your hand is filled with money,
and your head is filled with information, and your heart is empty,
then your life is very empty.
You realised today that so many people try to create happiness for themselves with the things around them.
But joy is something only believers have because joy is a fruit of faith.
And we are talking about the kind of joy that nothing in this world can destroy.
And that is the kind of joy that we as Christians ought to have.
As the Bible says in the book of John 14:27, "The peace Christ gives is not of this world".
Therefore, you should not trade your joy or peace for anything this world has to offer.
Exactly. So viewers around the world, let today's programme encourage you.
That no matter your situation - don't focus on what is happening in the world around you -
let your heart rise and seek the things that are above
and you will be richly blessed, in Jesus' name!
Thank you so much for joining us on today's episode of 'Changing LIves'.
Stay connected to Emmanuel TV to see more wonderful programmes here.
And we know the best is yet to come.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Olamide. Remain blessed.
Thanks for watching 'Changing Lives' - A Professor's Victory Over Immorality.
For comments and enquiries, send us an email to info@scoan.org or info@emmanuel.tv.
For comments and enquiries, call us on +234 (0) 8080800044 or +234 (0) 8088096917,
Share your testimony: +234 (0) 7086977000 or +234 (0) 8120271044.
Follow us on Social Media: facebook.com/tbjministries; twitter.com/scoantbjoshua
CHANGING LIVES
A production of SCOAN, in association with Emmanuel TV.